e
for
freyy
she she's taking advice for the the chat
will be around about half an hour and
then after the chat there'll be about 15
20 minutes for questions please do give
me a question there so much knowledge
with these two that it will it will
spark so much off even though you don't
think you will have questions and
sometimes the most basic questions
leester H there how are you sir um
are the ones that can provoke the most
insightful answers so please do engage
and respond there's a way too much
knowledge next to me not to do that I'll
hand over to you
then thank you thank you very much uh
well it it is a very special
conversation with two very special
inspirational individuals um if a little
cold um CLA Hines is a lecturer in
literature and creative writing at the
University of East Anglia where she also
leads on decolonizing curriculum work
across the faculty of Arts and
Humanities a fiction creative nonfiction
and theater monologues have appeared
Journal of international contemporary
writing the B short story award
Anthology Lighthouse itinerary journal
and Tangled Roots Anthology among other
publication it's also one and been
shortlisted for national awards in
2022 uh she you presented the BBC World
Service documentary my granny the slave
in connection with her research about an
enslaved ancestor in
Antiga previously worked as a BBC
documentary filmmaker and as the news
editor for black British newspaper voice
um and her media workers won national
creative industry Awards including a
George Viner Memorial award for
journalism a c race in the media award
and a royal television Society award
welcome CL thank
[Applause]
you
Professor Jason AR is a social
commentator presenter and public speaker
he's currently the 202 Professor
professorial chair of education at the
University of
Cambridge making him the youngest ever
black academic to hold a professorship
at Cambridge and one of the youngest
academics ever appointed to a
professorial chair in Ox brid's history
the context to is
important because the three years old
Jason as you some of you may or may not
know was diagnosed with global
development delay and autism spectrum
disorder he didn't speak until he was
seven couldn't read or write until he
was 18 and yet he's held professorial
posts at the universities of Glasgow and
Durham at Durham he was also Deputy
executive Dean for people in culture in
facility of social science and health he
holds an honorary professorship at
darham University and visiting
professorships at the Ohio State
University the University of Glasgow and
Mandela University and all of this is
important in the context of what we're
going to discuss I'll just redo a little
bit more Jason's also a trustee of the
runme trust the UK's leading race
equality Think Tank and outside of
Academia is written regular Fe he has
regularly written featured and spoken on
issues of race and racism in education
and Society for the guardian the Times
Higher Education supplement the BBC ITV
News CNN Good Morning America and CBS
there is more so so much more but I
think you may want to ask him about it
rather than listen to me so welcome
[Applause]
Jason now then I did think about how
best to approach this chat um you can
all see the uh title on it but I did I
thought to myself a better way to
approach it would be to make a statement
you two are two of the most
inspirational people I know so my first
question is with all that's going on
relating to race Society everything who
inspires
you CL
who inspires me okay that's a really
great question um so the writing that
I'm doing at the moment is about a um
ancestor of mine a woman ancestor who
was enslaved and ran away from a
plantation and lived in a cave and I
think about how resilient this young
woman was she was only young she was
about 17 how creative she would have
been the amounts of strength and
Ingenuity to
survive so there's something about the
history of black women that is really
important to me um my mother passed away
a few years ago but she was a really
inspirational figure for me um came over
as part of the Windrush
generation worked as a nurse in the
NHS work very
hard and um helped me to feel really
good about myself as a black
woman um yeah and there are some just
amazing women in my family from the
antean side of my family and I'm really
interested in the idea
of
um looking back through our mothers so
Virginia wolf who I've written
about uses this term in an essay called
A Room of One's Own and so part of my
research and writing has been doing
that has been following that sort of
idea who's gone before me who really
inspires me and writers as well you know
modern day writers like Bernardine
evaristo who's so amazing does so much
for black women um a writer called zoril
Hurston an African-American
writer she was someone who you know as a
teenager growing up surrounded by
literature in which I wasn't
reflected and um Their Eyes Were
Watching God in particular and her other
writing really inspired me and her use
of language black language her love of
Black
Culture it filled me with a sense of
power and respect in terms of who I am
and who's gone before me and that's so
important isn't it Jason to be able to
get that kind of inspiration that that
drives you and helps you to understand
yourself who inspires you hely I think
CLA points to some amazing people um CLA
herself is is immensely inspiring and I
guess I'm glad you said that yeah hugely
inspiring um as well as yourself um and
had the privilege of watching you on TV
in some way shape or form listening to
you on radio for 20 years so it's quite
surreal to be sat here with you now um
to be honest I'm always inspired by the
mundane like um my dad always said to me
there's a beauty in the mundanity of
life that you don't experience
when you kind of wrapped up in the rasat
Tas of what you would like life to be so
um I was very fortunate to have
experiences where I had not that long
ago probably eight years ago cleaning
jobs and working nights at
Sainsbury's um and the people I was
inspired by were the people who kind of
would always say things to me like
remember Jason you're very fortunate out
NE necessity dictates that I have to do
this for a living but you have choices
and one thing I never
underestimated um was how much courage
it takes to get up every morning and to
do something that you actually may not
want to do but because necessity
dictates so you have to do it and um
there's so many people who do who the
majority of people in the world we live
in have to enure this
reality and um my inspiration comes from
them because it allows me to put things
into perspective when I find work hard
and realize that actually you wake up
every day and you're doing you're living
the dream um and hard work doesn't
necessarily mean that you're going to
get what you deserve out of life and so
the other side of that is luck and and
I've been very very fortunate and it's
the same for fuity and luck that has sat
me in this position with you both
tonight thank you for that because um
you're right you both are very
inspirational figures um for many many
people I'm going to go with one if I'm
all
um because I I'm going to mention Dian I
love the outpouring of support and the
motion for her the statement that that
support
made um and I kind of tend not to waste
energy on the debates around whether
what was said about her was racist or
not because I think we can all make up
our own minds about that um I did want
to ask you however about how we go about
in our society
preserving that
energy and making sure that we're at
peace as we think about race and Society
clear so how we go about preserving the
energy of someone like that you would
otherwise use to be drawn into culture
wars and these debates about whether
something that we all know to be excuse
me racially offensive is can be describe
as such how to preserve that energy I
think my my view on that has changed
over the years years um I think that
through my work at the University
teaching and wanting to support students
and finding that students of color in
particular were um feeling
excluded and isolated and wanting to
support them and really trying
to have conversations about how we can
best support
students um and so and particularly you
know talking about
what's gone on since black lives matter
but there's been a lot of discussion
obviously since then um and I
think I kind of exhausted myself having
lots of conversations about race with
lots of
people and um and I remember when Rene
Edo's book came out why I know no longer
speak to white people about race and and
at the time I I felt as if I really
disagreed with her
um I felt well it's important to speak
out it's important to have conversations
and how am I going to do my job properly
if I'm not having these
conversations and while I say I am still
having those conversations and they
continue I think there's um there your
question is really interesting there's
there's an element there in which I
think now I'm thinking about well how do
I how do I look after myself and how do
I look after others within this so it
might mean thinking about when when am I
gonna have these conversations is it
worth having conversations with people
who just don't want to
hear and and if that's the
case that you know let me preserve my
energy so it's it's about being more
strategic yes I think about who to have
those conversations with when to have
those
conversations and the other thing is
gaining gaining support you know and
feeling like because I I uh work at
University of East Anglia I'm in a you
know quite a white space um H how do I
how do I ensure that I'm not isolated
that I'm I'm having to speak up I feel
like I'm having to speak up a lot um so
it's about trying to think about
supportive environments and connecting
with others to be able to have those
conversations because I know you're both
and you're very both very much about
positivity and moving forward and being
very selective about the way that use
that energy uh to ensure that you aren't
exhausting yourself emotionally as you
try to cover ground that you've covered
previously how do you go about it Jason
that's a good question I mean um I think
cla's covered kind of a lot of the areas
it's it's difficult I one of the things
I always think about is um in some
respects as a black or an ethnic
minority person you're kind of trained
in waiting your entire life with how to
deal with these situations and there's
never a point where it arrives it's
always on the preist of being there
so one of the things that I've learned
is um it was taught to me quite a young
age but I remember my mom kind of having
this big thing about giving people
compassion when they least deserve it
and a lot of times you're in the face of
absolute provocation you're faced with
having to show tremendous restraint yes
and I think restraint is very underrated
quality and I think black and ethnic
minority people constantly continuously
have to show restraint and in doing that
there is a process of internalization
which obviously can make people ill but
alongside that there's also a capacity
to continuously forgive in the face of
that provocation and it's something that
I think people shouldn't take for
granted and there is a a physical and
psychological toll that comes with that
but for me it always comes back to that
um compassion to to forgive and to
provide
opportunities
um to re into how people think about
certain things um so it's not for me to
tell people how to think but it's for me
to tell them what a reality is and I
don't think that um if a person of color
tries to explain what their racist
experience is I don't think it's for
anyone to contest I'm really glad you
say that because I I I I I certainly
found myself getting to a point where
um my color is not up for debate yeah so
there is never I I I now no longer take
part in is he right is X or Y saying yes
that is racist are they right it's not a
game show you know why am I doing this
um I do want to validate you though Dr C
because as a black woman
um it must have felt for you hearing
those words that were allegedly said in
the same way that the George Floyd
situation I've never watched the video
in its entirety shame on me maybe but I
just can't through that male traum of
see another male kit um and I'm sure
it's the same for yourself as well Jon
not watch it yet so I just want to and
please you don't you absolutely don't
have to cover that ground if you don't
feel you want to
but just how how did how did the franker
situation sit with
you um what I really like about the way
that you frame that question was that
you didn't repeat those
comments and I think part of the
difficulty was to hear those comments
repeated again and again through the
media and sometimes framed in ways which
didn't take issue with those comments or
didn't didn't do so
sufficiently so I think partly um it
wasn't that you know necessarily that
this person said these words so much as
how how how is this being discussed in
society how is this being played out um
I
think I think in some
ways it's made me feel as
if you know these these big comments are
made and similar to George Floyd these
you know there are these flash points in
which there's there's you know generally
a kind of horror from particularly from
you know liberal people or people who
who uh you know who who are interested
in questions of equality um but perhaps
less of a recognition that that those
sentiments are part of
life you know that these these questions
or these feelings are felt by me um as I
move through the world that they don't
have to be said
explicitly um so for me it's it's almost
like okay this has come to the surface
now at at least we can see we can see
what it is I I know what it is um yeah
it's awful but this is this this is
stuff this is real i' I've I've walked
through spaces I go through spaces and I
feel that hatred I feel that hatred um
in terms of not because of who I am but
of what what I who I represent or you
know being a black woman is is somehow
not not something that that people feel
um you know it's it's it's it's not it's
not validated or supported you know in
lots of different ways I mean it might
being you know kind of we we love
Beyonce or whatever it is but but there
there is there's a lot of hate um and
that you know that that's sad it's not
it's not just sad for me or other black
women it's sad for society yes and I
mean in a weird perverse way there is
almost
a a validation
that what we have known to be the case
suddenly was being played out in the
public domain and suddenly people were
getting that understanding of the kind
of thing that had been said for so many
years yeah
Jason I think I think the
business I was the only one that didn't
Flinch I'm definitely
one um I was going to say something that
um my mom has always said to me is that
the position of black women in society
is always permanently precarious yes um
and part of that permanent prity
normalizes the trauma that it's
inflicted upon black women it's just
normalized that people don't even Flinch
really um that's the concerning part
that people just see it as normal
discourse they don't actively try and
disrupt it you know you can have an
apology but not really an apology um you
can have consequences in play but they
don't really exist um you know you can
have really even K St not not really
condemn the comments in its full
entirety because at the current moment
the Whip's been taken off Dian and you
know that there's some of these things
that are kind of quite difficult and yes
there are reasons why the was taken
offer but actually it's about thinking
how do we demonize black women with
society and part of it it's it's kind of
it's organ it's almost like an organized
racket it it's just it's so normalized
what I find really disturbing is um the
fact that it's not disrupted through any
form of legislation policy you know um
societal commentary people just don't
disrupt it but I know that you two and
this is going to be a theme throughout
this evening you are both very much
about positivity and one of the things I
found to be very positive uh and we'll
we'll come back to this later on in the
chat but social media has disrupted it
because social media has given rise to
real power in the voices of the people
who have pushed back male and female
black and white against what has
transpired in relation to this but also
in answer to the question over the past
four years we've seen the rise of a
number of platforms where black voices
can feel empowered to push back against
the Orthodoxy and and against situations
just like this and that must give you
reasons for
optimism yeah I think that that rear
guard action I think it's always existed
through many many forms you know through
many civil there's been many
incarnations of civil rights black civil
rights activism and there's always been
a push back that push back has always
existed I think what's happening now is
that um there's been a harping back to
yester year where people have gone back
to being Unapologetic about it you know
you can't
kind of stifle or suppress those people
in the ways that systems have have
effectively done but not really achieved
um because those people's voices still
chime and still ring true and it'd be
interesting to kind of hear what you
both think on that as well because I I
do think we we always take our Direction
by what's happened before but you can
you can see almost people's chest
swelling as they kind of provide that
rear guard action to what they're
confronted with and that that in many
ways is quite arousing and it's and it's
seductive for a generation of people
actually looking at that and thinking
I'm going to take my queue from those
individuals CLA I think what I found
really heartening was um social media or
my social media not that I do loads of
social media don't do it don't do it um
we're filled with these um videos of um
people on you demonstrating outside
Hackney town hall and so that wasn't
something I I I um received through
mainstream media but it was it was huge
and it and it's very affirming um so
yeah you're you're right that this idea
of of kind of galvanizing people into
action and and really saying that you
know we're not taking this and your
point Jason about the way that that's
happened through throughout history you
know we can think about um you know
black lives matter and George Floyd
which is you know obviously really
important but you know there were so
many um flash points in history before
that in which black people were pushing
back you know from um Steven
Lawrence um uh you know new Crossfire s
1981 Morris yeah Olive Morris Bernie
Grant yeah Bernie Grant loads loads of
um loads of examples of times in which
black people have come together and and
really decided this this this is enough
and we're we're not accepting it
um if you're if you're a m if you're a
parent how do you navigate this working
landscape are we still telling our
children that you've got to work twice
as hard you've got to commit twice as
much to whatever Endeavor you are
involved in like our parents said to
us um I I think so yes really yeah I
think so yeah yeah my my m definit
definitely said to me you you know work
twice as hard that's what you need to do
that's twice as hard as somebody who is
white as someone who's white um told me
that there are different rules I
remember her having a conversation with
one one of my brothers saying look your
white friends can go and smoke cannabis
and that you know that's okay it's just
High Jinx but if you do that you know
you'll be criminalized so I was brought
up and and for me it was helpful to know
that that's what it is you know it's an
UNF system it's an unfair Society yes we
need to you know challenge it and take
issue with it but you know let's be real
that that is what we're facing and it's
it's sad but that's that's true and the
important aspect of this is that many
people who are white have used social
media and lots of big platforms to point
out that discrepancy that you highlight
and to recognize that there are
different rules for different
demographics Jason yeah I mean it's
always a shifting of sounds or a
shifting of goalposts um my own
daughter's 17 um and my son's nine and I
always think about when's the time to
have the chat so I think my dad had the
chat with me or my mom when I
was I think about
13 what did you say it was basically got
lot TI yeah no I mean the long and short
of it was if you ever get confronted by
the police like soft shoulders keep your
hands down speak with sof tone of voice
and make sure your body language is soft
and don't move
suddenly um and and it stayed with me my
whole life people always say you're
really softly spoken but that's what I
was told to
do take this as it so um I think it's
it's it's something that exists and look
there are a lot of black people by the
way who work twice as hard to get half
as much so it's not even an exact
science all the time that that ends up
being the case um and what CLA said
about what her mother said to a brother
but my parents said exactly the same
thing to me my brother there's so much
say that I've never smoked drank or done
drugs for the reason that if I did do it
I feel like the the consequence would be
very different for me um I always felt
that particularly as a teenager as in
when you get into kind of adulthood at
18 and also early 20s and and I was
always so Conant of that because I
always see my white counterparts getting
themselves into strike with the police
but they they'd be let off immediately
and i' and I'd be stopped and I'd kind
like I don't
drink yeah
so I love that insight into yourselves
I'm going to get into a little bit about
the two of you because you did an
interview a few days ago Dr CLA um You
can call me CLA it's all right no bells
and whistles
necessary yeah okay okay um but you have
earned it thank you um you were not
going to be an academic were you oh um
which interview is this not that there
are that many um I yeah I think um oh
there was absolutely no way I I thought
about being an academic absolutely no
way um I
um I think we're a similar age but but
when I was when I was growing up you
just there you know I remember I
remember a white colleague asking me um
not so long ago you know what was school
like for you you know and and just this
realization oh you didn't realize it was
it you know no one no one had any sort
of Bel you know the the standards the
expectations were so low um and uh you
know so the expectation was you know you
leave at 16 you know you you won't be
going to University people without even
knowing how I was doing at school you
know my career teacher literally taking
one look at me and and saying you get
out so so I had this feeling that
University wasn't wasn't for the likes
of me um I always love writing got into
the media which in some ways felt more
more open even though it was it was
difficult um and um and then in later
life went went to UEA and did an MA did
a PhD and someone said to me oh um would
you ever become an academic and I just
laughed in their face there Absol no way
that's happening um
so uh yeah it it's just it it just felt
like it it just wasn't it wouldn't be on
my radar there was no one I saw around
me who who who was who was I mean I had
um I mentioned in this interview the one
I think you're referring to uh a friend
of mine um Robert Beckford who's a prent
black academic but yeah he's fantastic
and has really supported me but outside
of that I didn't see people at my
University um so so yeah I'm just amazed
that I'm here I'm still like oh my gosh
I'm I'm Dr CLA am I really absolutely
but you should own it and it's the
reason why I I refer to as doctor
because the the it's not just academic
work that has gone into that it's
emotional societal work that has gone
into it defying the odds and when we
talk about race in society the
difficulties that you have to surmount
the obstacles that you have to get past
to be where you are is it true there is
61 black professors out of 26,000 across
out to 23,000 yeah that's right yeah so
the the the numbers are really really
low and the other thing is when we do
have um you know many of those um
professors of color uh coming from
overseas um so the fact that we're you
know we're black British academics I
think is is pretty pretty fantastic but
yeah we definitely need more black women
um coming into
[Applause]
Academia Jason yeah I mean follow that
no I don't I don't intend to I bow to
cla's brilliant
um it's it's yeah it's 24,000 professors
um the number 210 black presses 61 of
black women um yeah um black women
outnumber black men in the academy by
two to one so you know there's some
brilliant research that's been done um
around the L 300 so it's 300 black women
that should have been black female
professors and how they've been denied
which is why you know we really need to
continue to interrogate these structures
because what we can't continue to the
the academy is not blessed with you know
abundance and abundance of kind of
amazing black academics and the reason
why I say that is because there's so
many obstacles in place for them to even
get there in the first place so the ones
that we do have it's really important
that we find ways to ensure that they
end up where they need to be because
there are too many people that have
fallen by the way through systemic and
institutional kind of through the
apparatus of systemic and institutional
racism which is which I've been
Unapologetic about saying and that's
always been the case especially for
black women in the academy so I think
that's something that we kind of really
need or at least in my work I'll
continue to address but we we do need to
address that I wasn't going to ask this
and I know we don't have a lot of time
where's Mandy is Mandy how long do I
have Mandy five minutes anyone want 10
minutes 15 minutes or you can five a
little bit more
time okay all right okay I'll take I'll
be very quick with this one
but very often one of the things I find
people say
is this is the way we've always done it
and so it's not necessarily Sinister or
what we would characterize as racist but
they would just say it's the way things
have always been done do you think there
is that complacency or do you think that
um there is clearly we live in the real
world and in some at some level there is
a willingness to uphold the structure as
we put it but what are your thoughts
around
that either can take that
one I I understand the idea when you
don't know better you don't do better
yes but I I think when you do know
better it becomes a choice and I think
far too often people actually do know
better and they make a concerted choice
to not do the right thing and I think as
a society we would do better to
actually interrogate why people choose
to make that choice of course Free Will
allows individuals to do what they like
but I think Free Will at the expense of
the humanity of another individual needs
to be questioned and needs to be
challenged and all too often I think
we've we've assimilated into this
culture where it's okay to oppress
particular minority groups without
Challenge and and and that I find that
staggering
CL um well I was thinking about the
question in relation to um
universities um this idea that okay
there's a particular tradition there's a
particular way of doing things um and um
and sometimes uh the idea of kind of
diversity is pitted against sort of
educational
Excellence but part of teaching
Excellence is about um changing changing
Styles approaches content so we don't
teach in the way that we did aund years
ago you know we don't necessarily have
everything as being kind of you know
we're the experts we're just kind of
going to force it on you you remember
things and and tell it back to us and
write an essay it's discursive there are
different ways of doing things different
ways of engaging PE people um you know
use sort of creative methods so so the
ways in which we teach have changed but
the content needs to change as well you
know
there are different views different
perspectives different
ideas um so and if if we stay if we stay
if we do things exactly the same same
way it it just makes nothing in society
stays the same not fashion not music not
food everything everything moves on and
um you know but there but it's
interesting that in certain spaces or
certain spheres there's a there's that
kind of resistance and that that's a
really good point because obviously I I
work in journalism and I see certain
areas o of my industry characterize that
move to want to progress and to learn
more and widen the sphere of learning in
terms of decolonizing the curriculum as
something to be derided rather than to
be embraced in the same way as you say
we would develop music we would develop
art we would develop so many other areas
of society um and so when somebody talks
about wanting to do that with the
curriculum it's characterized as a
threat to the curriculum rather than an
opportunity for so many students
watching this who are here who aren't
here but watching on on on on online
will be able to benefit from what are
your views on
that I always kind of go back to what
the purpose of education is which is for
me it's always been about this values
and belief system around preping people
to take their place within society and
as custodians of educational spaces part
of that responsibility is to provide
people to talk here to navigate a
Multicultural multiethnic Society and I
think all too often in education I I
often question how well are we equipping
people to go back into society to go
into society to be able to navigate a
Multicultural multiethnic Society and I
think that always has to be the premise
because fundamentally being able to
a society like
this requires huge levels of diplomacy
it requires an accepting of difference
it requires in accepting that actually
people experience kind of intersectional
inequalities and what might that look
like it requires us to kind of sit in an
empathetic space you know to kind of
stand or at least yeah stand alongside
people in capacities of allyship
whatever that may be across the
intersectional Spectrum so I think those
things are important I think it is
really important particularly with race
because there is a normalization with
racism and a Nostalgia about how things
used to be um and almost this kind
of I don't know like
this this kind of colonial Amnesia and
if you're not colonially compliant then
the next thing that accompanies that is
well if you don't like it you can leave
and I and I think it's it's important we
we're better than that we're better than
that and I and I think we need to move
beyond that because actually it's to
everyone's advantage to understand that
actually the best way to navigate
difference is to have an understanding
of where we've come from where we've
been and that allows us to think about
where we're going absolutely and an
interconnected world now as digital
media allows us to be there is an even
greater emphasis on needing to have that
understanding
CL yeah um yeah we definitely need we
need to have that we need to have that
understanding and I think the
interesting thing when with the
conversations around decolonizing the
curriculum was um was that the the
impetus was coming from the students
themselves who were feeling short
Changed by their education because um
you know this idea that there are
expected ways in which we we think about
objects um and um yeah there might be I
mean within literature creative writing
there are some you know obviously great
canonical writers and no one's saying
get rid of the cannon no it's just that
there are fantastic writers outside of
the cannon and surely we should also be
you know including them and thinking
about New Perspectives new ways of
looking at the world so no so but it it
the discussion around it was so has been
so misguided
and frankly
bizarre um you know and it makes you for
me I'm thinking why you know what what
is it what is this Terror about kind of
oh well you know we'll never we'll never
you know Shakespeare is going to be
thrown out of the window and trashed or
something for some you know bizarre
black writer I mean it's just that's
that's not what's
happening line your questions up I've
only got a couple more for uh CLA and
for Jason and then I'll be handing over
to you to ask your questions um I live
in
London Dr CLA you live uh in East
Anglia and you're in London as well
aren't
you%
th%
um does your understanding of racism
depend on where in the country you
live in
2024 I think so
um and this is actually working here as
a close of work time which is London um
South K South London and I worked at
several different um places um in the
north um and including Scotland and I
think understandings around race are
completely different based one on
diaspora and populace so the further up
north I went the small percentage of of
black and ethnic minority people there
were so I worked at Durham for three
years for example and in the Northeast
um 98% of the Northeast is is is white
so it's it's a very small populace of of
black or ethnic minority people there
so understandings around that in some
respects are still quite
embrionic um but there was a willingness
um for people to kind of learn more in
terms of what that may have looked like
because obviously what what the
Northeast was populated by was um five
institutions and two in
particular at the University of
Sunderland and tside University and
North umbrea sorry three that had huge
kind of um South Asian populaces at
those um institutions so people are
beginning to understand a bit more about
what that was like and how that
transpired um and what I would say is
that being spoiled you know when you
brought up in London you're spoiled in
some respects um and I hadn't
appreciated that until I worked in
Liverpool All Leads darham Scotland Glo
to be pacific um and it it is different
it is very different um but what what is
interesting is you go to a place like
Liverpool for example that has this Rich
incredible history um not just for the
sport but it was also um a a port a a a
a a colonial output and how they engage
with that history there's always been a
t around how they engage with that
history but then you go to kind of LA
and you meet people within those areas
and you learn more about kind of what
the kind of tox death riots meant and
how it kind of simulated across the UK
at the time you know in terms of in the
Midlands you know in in Tottenham in
Brixton Etc so it it is different but
what's really interesting in all of
these places that everyone has their
unique story to tell about how they've
negotiated or navigated
race and racism and kind of diaspora in
those spaces and in some respects it's
um it's hugely inspiring but it does
always make me feel very grateful that
at a time when my parents first came to
the UK as a black person as an immigrant
you didn't have a choice about where you
where you were placed and and I grew up
on the councel estate and I'm very aware
that I could have been moved to any I
could have been moved to Parts Unknown
and it's it's but for the grace of God
that was very fortunate not only did we
we were brought up in London but we
stayed in London when actually at times
you know that wasn't always necessarily
going to be the case because in the mid
90s black families were being moved all
over the
UK
CLA um so well as you noted I I live in
East Anglia um norwi and
um so yeah experiences of racism are
different there I think when I first
moved to Norwich I moved to um do my m
um quite a while ago and I remember
going onto the campus and seeing one
black student way in the distance and
going up to him and saying where are all
the black people and he said oh there
were 20 of us I was like oh
dear um so um so yeah it was it felt
like an is quite an isolating experience
and um I remember my first trip so I'd
feel the need to just keep getting back
to London and I would um I I I remember
driving down to London and filling up
the boots of my car with kind of
plantains and sweet potatoes and hair
products and like feeling okay I need to
surrounded my surround myself with this
stuff because because because it was
like that this is my sort of comfort
this is this is making me feel more like
you know more kind of at home um and um
and I got involved with Black History
Month in in Norfolk and I remember
feeling uh wow it feels like this feels
like London 20 years ago but um there is
you know there's a there is a small but
growing you know kind of Multicultural
community and um and I think things have
changed over the years there's uh
there's a Black History Month tour in in
Norwich which is amazing which debunks
that idea about Norwich being this sort
of White City um you know black people
have been coming in and out of Norwich
for you know centuries there's a GU
there was a a famous Victorian circus
owner called Pablo F who lived in who
lived in Norwich and there's a student
building that um that has been named
after him so so it's about you know
let's change change up the kind of
narratives before it was Nelson you know
everything's like Norfolk it's Nelson's
County
Nelson Nelson Nelson Street Nelson Pub
Nelson everything which was a bit sort
of strange for me because then I go back
to you know go to Antiga I shouldn't say
go back I wasn't born there but I go to
Antiga which I do often and the whole
there's a whole South part of the island
is is sort of Nelson's dockyard so I'm
like gosh I can't get away from this
Nelson guy he's everywhere so um so yeah
things have things things have changed
but I do I do feel need to I go to
London regularly um I visit I've got
really great family in Antiga and so and
although I'm born and raised in this
country I feel as if um antea is is
another home for me in London so I keep
myself healthy and set feeling good yeah
I've got so many more questions around
raise pay cap diversity whatever else
but I do want to take questions I will
give
particular uh prominence and priority to
anyone who's called
Nelson but I'll start over
here I think this is
compulsory um I'm intrigued to know what
how you respond to the fact that our
government has a number of very senior
people of color who would you like to
give that question
to panel okay who wouldd like to take
that one
me
okay uh how do I feel about that that's
um it's an interesting one I mean sense
of it how do I make sense of it okay
I'll make sense of it by saying this
that we need to think about not just the
individuals people are saying well how
how can how can people who are brown be
saying that diversity is is wrong how
can they be so quick to say that you
know racism doesn't exist but we need to
think about the systems and structures
it's these aren't this isn't about
individuals this is about society and
this is about um systems and structures
and um the legacy of
colonialism that has meant that the you
know these ideas are in place and also
that interestingly all these ideas about
oh well you know diversity and some
people are getting advantages I mean
there was an interesting article in the
guardian that was saying well if if
anyone's doing well out of out of you
know pushing certain politics which are
anti- equality and anti- diversity it's
certain you know brown people in in
polit high political places you know how
how well are they how well are they
doing it you know it's better not to get
certain people to um it's better perhaps
for some people to think okay well you
know we don't have to some white people
don't need to speak up about these
things because others well I've probably
said too much now I probably shouldn't
have I should have let you take it I'll
come in I've got you I've got you like
help me out me
out I think part of the problem is that
um it reminds me of something my dad
said like the only concept that is
colorblind is individualism and
selfishness and I don't think we should
confuse
um individualistic based desire
over representation I think it's a very
important thing because a lot of um the
parliamentarians of
color that currently reside they are
really being used as mules to push
agendas that really don't benefit um the
greater good so for example when you
have parliamentarians who are you know
rubbishing things for example like
critical race Theory or um saying
diversity or kind of this with a woke
agenda
um the cost for them to say that the
cost to them I guess when they weigh it
up as minimal in respect to what they
may gain politically in career from a
career point of view speaking in terms
of the trajectory they face so I I often
tell people when I'm I've heard
questions like this before and one of
the things I always emphasize to people
is that you
know we shouldn't
align
naked aggressive ambition with
mobilizing the agenda of race equality
because they're two different things and
that kind of animal Instinct that some
people have and where they're happy to
exploit agendas to further their own
cause is really not exclusive to black
or brown parliamentarians it's it's
something that actually happens in
politics full stop um as we've seen
Boris Johnson do
to brilliant effect with the um with the
referendum campaign around the Europe
around brexit can I just ask you before
we move on what's your view on the
question that you've just
asked
um I think it's a terrible
situation if you'd have asked me bearing
in mind I'm now in my 70s if you'd have
asked me 30 years
ago which political party would have
senior people of color leading the
government I would never have
anticipated that so I think it's
important not to
underestimate the
mechanisms and priorities and
manipulations of the conservative party
as an institution I think they're a
wider structured I'm completely
sympathetic to that but um they're quite
clever you
know the I asked for your opinion
because person who microphone's going to
go next to is the editor of the biggest
black newspaper in the country I was um
not anymore I'm actually here now in
Cambridge University um but um actually
just respond to to that that last point
this is not my question um I mean I
think that the the fact that we have uh
so many uh black and Asian uh people who
are pushing a very negative um
narratives around race equality that are
every opportunity they can possibly um
have to to actually hit back uh against
people who are pushing for uh racial
Justice is actually in some ways a badge
of honor and a recognition of the fact
that social media in particular and you
know the black lives matter movement and
everything that's going with it and that
uh you know sense of um you know looking
back into history uh and you know
recognizing the the the history of
Britain and you know and how Britain has
has you know benefited and got rich uh
by colonialism and and slavery you know
those are very live things that are
happening on the ground and then you
have a counter reaction so in some ways
I think we should actually you know
recognize actually that this
is not a a sign of success but actually
a sign of contest really but my my
question was actually about um uh
Academia um and the fact that we have so
many uh so so few uh black professors
and black academics
uh in in general and I guess my question
really is is about the fact that it
feels like there's a real dichotomy
between um you know people who really uh
you know Embrace um you know um
diversity sort of quote unquote you know
when it's when there no cost uh when
when it's a case of um you know
embracing you know uh even teaching you
know anti- you know Colonial um uh know
or texts and things like that um and
there's dichotomy between that um and
and actually listening to Black
academics and being
challenged um uh by them and and that
you know is a very uncomfortable
situation it just feels like sometimes
they can coexist together uh and so in
that situation how do we actually break
through and make a change there so so so
just the question question what what
what is the actual question U yeah what
do we do what do we do what do we do
about
that so so the the context of that
question did you pick it up do you want
to pick pick it up great to see by way
um so in I think in terms of diversity
and diversity in the kind of lecture
space or the classroom the educative
space I think one of the things that's
um that's difficult is that I think for
a lot of black academics in those
um there is a hypers surveillance
already there so a lot of the things
that they want to discuss um there is a
policing of that which happens um
through colleagues micromanaging the
content and what is discussed and it
also happens subliminally through what
students think and say and sometimes
students you know it can be the tail
that Waggles the dog the tail that
Waggles dog and you've you've got this
situation where students can make the
lives of black academics in particular
very very difficult particularly black
women um and so in those spaces what do
you mean by that sorry j so very often
if um students are disgruntled with what
they are experiencing from a pedagogical
point of view they have um they can
provide scores at the end of modules and
these scores are quite consequential for
promotion um or being considered for
promotion um a lot of the research I've
done is that out of this process black
women are the most negatively affected
by that and a lot of it comes from
people who who take om brdge with not
wanting to discuss for example issues
around black feminism um as a
theoretical construct or some of the
kind of really tentative issues around
racism which there's a fragility that
people experience in that environment as
a result the uncomfortability then kind
of results in people being actually I
didn't enjoy that pedagogical experience
the only reason I'm interrupting is
because CA you're nodic so maybe you
want to pick up from what Jason say um
yeah it's it's a that's a tricky one so
um I I do feel as if I have I'm not just
saying because I'm employed by UEA I'm
not going to say oh it's it's all it's
you know I'm not g to speak them up just
because I'm employed by them but I do
feel like the um I feel supported by my
head of school I feel supported by quite
a few people and that hasn't always been
the case so I think it it helps it helps
to have support there yes and um and
there is yeah as Jason said I'm I'm I'm
always aware of that I'm always aware
that that sometimes
um sometimes you know you can feel
resistance or that there are particular
questions that that people are asking
you that they probably would be asking
of your colleagues and um and that I
mean it's going back it's similar to
that question about um about having to
try twice as hard it's like well that
that's that's the terrain we're we're
working with and it and it is difficult
and it does pose
difficulties um and or we can do is the
best we can and feel that we're we're
supported by our colleagues but but we
do we do have to bear in mind you know
who's in the room what what are they
asking of us and and and you know where
you know where where is this guy it is a
difficult situation but but it's it's
about finding ways in which to navigate
it as as effectively as possible I've
got a feeling that feedback from here is
going to be particularly positive we've
got another question over here we've got
one over there as well do we have
time thank you we'll go to on the left
here oh we've got third one over there
but we'll go to on if we can we'll keep
our answers to these ones tight so we
can get everybody
in uh thank you so much for this
opportunity my name is Esa from Kenya uh
mine is really a concern that translates
into a question uh trying to understand
with all this knowledge that is out here
about understanding The Continuous
acceptance of the black uh Society
especially as for Africa into a
subordinate position in anything
development Global finance and the
academias are aware of it even since
1881 it's been written Walter Rodney has
Al also wrote about it Missouri and
everybody else and currently a lot of
contemporary Scholars are writing about
it then why is it with all this
knowledge are we still signing or
getting into Parts uh that are actually
putting us into to subordinate positions
in terms of getting uh Financial advice
getting financial aid and Visa checking
on what is happening on the other side
of capital flights multinational
corporations acting as looting machines
why why are we not concerned enough to
get out of that uh situation that brings
everyday
inequality somewhere in Africa somewhere
in Kenya in Nairobi and not so many
people are able to come here and voice
their concerns thank you it's a good
question it's probably a thesis I'm
going to try and get an answer from one
of you maybe in about 30 seconds to a
minute do you want to take that CLA yeah
fine fine I mean I can only really speak
in terms of my discipline in terms of
teaching literature and creative writing
and say although um uh you know it's
about trying to what I try to do is just
um exposed my students to a wide range
of texts and African writers are part of
that you know gooo wongo or um you know
who whoever it is Ju Just um just a
broad range of texts and and also
different different perspectives as well
I'm teaching a feminist writing class
and um you know there's an idea of
feminism as being kind of very white and
European but thinking about you know
what are the experiences of African Wom
women um let's look at African feminisms
like there there are lots of different
ways in which we can explore the
richness of African culture and African
knowledge African philosophy and um so I
try to do that as as much as I can and I
I think that we should and you're right
we we're just not including enough
enough of this you know amazing
knowledge that that is in the world it's
been disparaged for so long and it's
important that we we take it on
let's take our question over here with
the right and we've got a couple more
thank you for all of your questions so
far go ahead well I'd firstly like to
say thank you so much it's been really
inspiring just hearing you speak um from
my experience I have with every
institution I've either studied in or
worked in I have always experienced some
kind of racism and I was just kind of
wondering what your experiences were and
if you feel like it's Neary
to kind of sacrifice defending yourself
in to reach positions of
success that's a great question um no I
think there's a cost and it's is a
residual one I think um what goes out
what goes in must come out so if you
know you can't it's a difficult thing to
suppress over a period of time but um I
am a really big believer in terms of
dignity and how one carries
and it's difficult and that's what I was
talking about earlier about restraint I
think um the thing that we don't have
the luxury of of not being is we we're
always racially ascribed and with those
racial ascriptions there's a set of
stereotypes and ascriptions that come
with that so for example the angry black
woman or the aggressive black male like
you just if I want to be angry I can't
really afford to do it in the workplace
which is can I ask you if that's the
case because I I agree with you you
we're all in senior positions and but
you're right there is that cost that
comes with that sometimes we might want
to express ourselves and we think well
if we do we jeopardize our space we risk
our space but there is a cost to that
and it's an emotional cost because you
do withhold it there is a high rate of
mental health issues particularly with
black men so is it still the case that
we should exercise that restraint in
your opinion or do we need to now that
we have that awareness to address it
differently when I say restraint I I
think there the
initial like um and and and I guess what
you what you learn to do is kind of
think right how can I get my point
across um recognizing that there are all
these kind of permutations in terms of
how I how I how I place this point or
how I verbalize this point and I think
that people should always feel the need
to be able to do that um but
unfortunately there is a dance you have
to do and you have to self in some ways
but I think there's a way to do it I
think I would say this but I think we're
we're very nient and we found ways of
circumnavigating these situations since
time oforia so there are ways to do it
um and I think there's a quiet Authority
and dignity that black and ethnic
minority people have that actually
they're not given the opportunity to tap
into enough because they're racially
ascribed so quickly before they even say
anything but I always think there's the
opportunity to tap into that quiet
Authority and I can stay like this and I
can say something quite profound in
terms of making a very a point that
could cause a lot of friction in terms
of something I disagree with that work
and there's not really anything someone
could level at me not been aggressive
I've not raised my voice body language
has stayed exactly the same and these
are all things that we shouldn't have to
do because my white cter parts are
allowed to be expressive and angry and
flamboyant and it's kind of seen as like
I a got a zest for life or you know if I
do it I'm combative or I'm angry but I I
think there's A's a Qui Authority that
we've always exercised and you know when
I think of people like Angela Davis or I
think of B Hooks and people like people
that I've always taken my direction from
they've always had that same sense of
quiet Authority and it's it's it's a
really powerful thing and something that
we we have to utilize in these difficult
times CLA just pick up on that because
obviously there are lots of young black
women who look at somebody in a position
that you are in and that's a burden that
you have to carry even at sometimes when
you do want to smack your fist as Jason
just did
um so just answer that question very
quick um well I I agree with Jason and I
think I think I don't I like to feel
like I have a certain amount of
Integrity that I'm myself but I know
that I need to present myself in a
particular way and I think that's
something that I've learned growing up
that that you know you have to be super
polite you have to be super calm and in
some ways that feels kind of natural to
me but I don't think you have to
compromise
you know the fact that we're even
talking about race I think I I think
could be seen as for some people
problematic some some of some colleagues
um colleagues of color don't even want
to talk about race so so there there is
a certain amount of of kind of you know
weighing things up but I I I think I
think you can do it thank you thank you
very much we've got one question over on
the right side then we'll take the
question over on the back but first this
one over here we will get to you okay
get am I next sorry thank you very much
40 plus years ago I was lucky enough to
attend an amazing school called akan
Bley in North London very diverse school
um we my parents were on the March where
Blair Peach was killed every Friday I
stood outside South African Embassy and
we marched on the BMP Bookshop in South
London to to close in very scary
circumstances and some of the rhetoric I
here now really really saddens me in
terms of what what what's coming if I
look up on the screen in terms of the
word progress it say making real
progress and I this it's probably not a
question for 10 n but if you had that
that ability to say to those people who
could make that progress what what do we
need to do now because 40 plus years on
from where my family and I did those
things and those actions I don't think
the progress quite is been as fast as we
would like to to have been but if you
had that ability to say you know where
do we need to go next what do we need to
do to make that progress happen quicker
um I think we need to I I think that the
spirit that you talked about which is
about using our voices and and making it
clear what we're not happy with as a
society coming together is is really
important um I think that we should use
our consumer power and and decide okay
if if um you know if uh if certain
newspapers are being really obnoxious
don't buy them you know if C certain
people don't want to employ black people
or say nacy things about black people
don't don't you know don't support them
um and the other thing I think that's
come out recently is uh after black
lives matter people were saying you know
what do I do now and I think what I'd
like to see is more white people support
you know there was lots of talk about
all allyship and that idea about you
know anti-racism means proactive you
know it's about proactive support and I
know there are lots of people who who
are supportive and you know many of you
here I'm sure are really supportive and
I'd like to see you know things like we
had that conversation about parenting
and the talk you know to what extent the
white parents having that talk with
their children about you know what
society looks like you know um I'd like
to see that you know when my daughter's
at school and she's experiencing racism
that her friends are are are you know
vigorously saying this isn't okay but at
the moment there seems to be this sort
of people are scared to talk um and the
far right is is making use of that you
know that there there's a fear about oh
well if I say this maybe it'll be the
wrong thing maybe um use the wrong
terminology no speak out and be
supportive and that will help to to make
changes now I've going to give you a
choice do you want to answer that
question or do you want to take the next
one uh take the next one so that we get
everyone in all right let's take that
one over there on the far right and then
we'll come back on to the far left on
the far right the
[Laughter]
far go
ahead sorry just a bit louder just to
get that microphone closer I was going
to say there are few people here and I
hope that means that most people feel
that there isn't a problem out there
because the things that have brought out
people on Street and where there are
blackards are obscene things that have
happened and I think most of the
population feels that the people that
they are and that they live around that
that would never be part of their lives
most people are good I think there is a
problem here in actually recognizing
that we all range from pale pink to very
deep pink and we need to perhaps move
forward into the future with different
terminy so that we are not separated
there is just a diffusion of color
really that exists um we need
to you actually attended some of these
um BNF parades that I was too afraid to
go to and I remember saying to my
parents all the white guys are there and
we're the only people who are not
turning up because we're just too afraid
and the things that we do need to do is
one thing that I really found Val
the entire evening is are these few
words that your father said to you when
you were young when it came to
presenting yourself before any policeman
or any figure of authority and that is
something that I think can be said in
school assemblies all over the country
just so that other people and other
young people have an idea of what your
life experience is like because racism
exists because other people don't know
how it feels to experience a different
reality there is so much perfect
rhetoric out there all the legislation
is worded perfectly but there is such a
thing as a gar club and most of those
individuals are not sitting here today I
wish they had turned up the Cambridge
Union needs to have further debates
about with with titles that are a lot
more provocative than than this
institutionalist racism exists within
the criminal justice system which makes
it a failure it absolutely we have a
very Gentile conversation here today and
all these people are lovely in fact
these are the converts these are not the
people that we need to be speaking with
the Press is
utterly irredeemably irresponsible with
the way that it is actually constructed
itself you were too polite I do have to
I think maybe there isace here for a Mal
discuss well you know it's a really good
point it's a really good point about
the
ands
station and I spoke with somebody before
the station had open station
only opens for a few hours and um had a
discussion
and nothing has happened
since and I said a few words about how
important this was but before I went to
Parkside I actually wrote to the MP Mr
Anthony Brown three emails went by and
his secretary responded to me what would
you could you please summarize three
times in em what you would like Mr Brown
to do or what you hope to achieve and I
think that was the point at which I said
there's really nothing more than I can
do well I didn't actually give up I
actually wrote back an email saying I'll
come up with a summary and maybe I will
but it's fills me with Despair and this
is in a month in which Dian Abott has
been has
had an appalling
and the voices have been
mute it's beyond what is acceptable and
the frustration that you expressed right
there we we we speaking about it earlier
in terms of the voices that have being
empowered in this month physically going
to the town hall and being able to show
that vocal support but also using the
different forms of media to be able to
do that and when we have these
conversations here they're designed to
find a way through because we've grown
up in decades of anger and frustration
and the unwillingness or the inability
to be able to express that anger that
you express right there so what we then
have to do for just forgive me um is
then find strategies and ways to empower
ourselves so that we can go forward and
actually subvert the structures that are
intent on making sure that we don't have
a voice please go
ahead tell one anecdote of something
that's happened two days
ago in London Bridge I was walking um in
a in a small supermarket and
um a young white man uh he must have
been his between 20 and 30 came into the
store and drinking rather a lot and he
had picked up two bars of chocolate and
uh he suddenly turned to the security
man and he said why are you looking at
me why are you looking at me which was I
can I felt well that's a perfectly
reasonable question to ask you been feel
upset that he's looking at you and uh
the security man who happened to be
completely Brown um looked at him and
didn't say anything but he was
there and another Brown assistant who
was in the store came up so there are
now two brown people and there's me
standing there and uh the white guy came
up and he said you know it would be
different if it was you what do you
think would you be would you be doing
this if I was black and U he was
absolutely right in feeling that heat
came from his heart and I in between the
security guy and him and he' thrown the
two bars onto the ground this and it in
a really aggressive way and I remember
thinking that I've seen this before in
another time in another space because
I'm now 60 when the security man would
have absolutely wielded the the the guy
out through the shop and it would all
have been finished
but he turned to me and said you
what are you doing and I said I'm trying
to save you and he was shaken and he
said what do you
mean and I just thought that this could
so suddenly get ugly where the police
are called and he would be in trouble
and all I had to do was to stop that
from happening it it hurt me to think
that he might trouble for feeling what
he was feeling with all his heart and
part of this debate that I came to today
because I'm exhausted I've been awake
since 4 this morning is that I want to
say that there is real fear among people
it isn't just the one side when people
say we don't want the voke agenda which
is perfectly valid and reasonable that
there is another side of humanity do
understand why there is a need for vote
discussion and please excuse me
everybody quite all right this is not as
you rightly say a gentile discussion
this is a real issue that affects lives
affects all of our day-to-day lives
hopefully we can get you guys back here
because I mean an Aron art is clearly
nowhere near enough to be able to
discuss something that really does stir
up a lot of passion for a lot of people
so your
contribution
we will take one more on the left over
here thank you for all of your questions
by the way uh go ahead thank you very
much and thank you so much for your
honesty and in and in sharing what you
have this evening um my my question is
is really related to um uh what can as
always what else can be done to
readdress balance and and particularly
around
narrative um so um um that's where the
question's going um and and education in
particular um and um the the point that
I would like to raise uh is very much um
about um what has been taught across
Generations in terms of of history and
obviously some of those things are being
addressed but now um you know sort of um
as a mature person I have only recently
discovered um so I'm not alone is what
I'm saying I've only recently discovered
that there were in there there are
incredible amounts of History actually
that that have never been told and
therefore you know were unable to
celebrate um the tremendous works you
know and I think of of musicians um um
classical um musicians classical writing
classical music writing that has never
ever been um you know it's just not
taught um you know um from um you know
people of color that have been written
by people of color has never ever been
taught so um you know as a society we
lack
richness because you know we don't we
don't know what has existed we don't
know um we're unable to celebrate it
because we don't know it existed want to
direct that too um so um I culture well
both actually because I'd like to hear
what you both would have to say on that
but in terms of Education thinking about
future Generations how can that be
addressed well I think I think we are as
a society starting to address that I
went to a classical music concert the
other day um UEA Orchestra and they were
playing an African-American composer
called Florence price and and um who who
has been who who is a composer who who
just wasn't celebrated in the past and
um I went to an exhibition of an artist
called Frank
Walter um again from well from Antiga so
um and he was a really prolific artist
um who who wasn't celebrated in the past
but now they're you know just last year
there was an exhibition in London so I
think we are we are we are doing that
work artists writers are doing that work
I'm trying to do that work in telling
the story of of my ancestor and also
other black women from the past it's
really important work it's Rich Work and
as you said it it supports Society it
supports education um but yeah I I think
you know that's something and also these
are there are opportunities here for
academics for writers for uh you know to
to restore and recover these uh you know
great people from the past do you want
to take the last word yeah I was going
to say I think the British historical
Cannon has has thrived on um positioning
on on aasia it's thrived on aasia and I
guess um in terms of embracing that
history in its fullest
sense it does need to think about the
things that make up that historical
Cannon you know not this kind of
nostalgic eraser that has always
transpired and I think part of that um
or a narrative that has suited that is
has positioned black and ethnic and
Indigenous people as always oppressed um
or being in some form of subordination
or enslavement and as you as you've
mentioned and as the amazing cla's
mentioned there are so many stories and
Rich histories in terms of our
contribution to not only domestic
Society but Global Society so I think
sitting in that and recognizing some of
the uncomfortability and what people
people have done to Traverse those
spaces in spite of the kind of the the
horrors that have been experienced I
think is really important and sitting
with that uncomfortability is also I
think an an essential part because I
think part of not wanting to engage with
that is the uncomfortability of oh it's
a bit it's a bit sticky and and the
fragility kind of kicks in and before
you know it you're managing the entire
discourse it's about really embracing it
in its fullest kind of WS and all
and
Britain does have a past that is
problematic and it needs to recognize
that um and I think you know that is an
important part in terms of moving
forward and also recognizing the
entirety of the histor his historic
British Cannon there we must end I know
there must be so many more questions
that you might want to ask and certainly
get answered um hopefully we may be able
to get these two
incredible incredible people back here
again you incredible as well Darren you
know right assistant editor of Daily
Mirror I will just say this very quickly
um this is a starting point for a
discussion you will never ever get any
discussion on Race folded neatly into a
box with a nice bow on the top there is
too much hurt too much history too much
trauma too much daytoday lived
experience
and too much
unquantifiable too many unquantifiable
elements connected with it so the
antidote to that is to learn to read to
listen to talk and to ensure that we all
regardless of our level of experience
demographic place that we live in the
country we keep on learning not just
from people who look like us but from
people who don't look like us so that
together we can make strides and maybe
come back here and share that learning
with that I want to say thank you to
Jason
Ary I actually should have said
Professor Jason
sorry and Dr
CLA and also to you thank you very much
inde